Hey, what's up guys? My name is The
Cherno. Welcome back to my C++ series.
Today we're going to be talking all
about how you can store any kind of data
in a single variable in C++. A lot of
you are probably thinking, well, yeah,
you can do that with a void pointer. And
yes, that's true. And I'll have a video
about void pointers coming soon in the
future. However, this is a much better
way. It's a safer way and it's a C++ 17
brand new way of doing things. I've had
this kind of mini series lately on how
we can store different types of data in
single C++ There's something called STD
optional, STD variant, and now we're
going to be talking about STD any. And
I've already made videos about the other
two. So, if you haven't seen the video
about optional data or the video about
how we can store multiple variables,
multiple data types in a single
variable, then check out those videos.
They'll be linked up there. So, now
we're kind of here at the end. We're up
to the point where using STD any, we can
store anything. And I think that the
bigger question here is not how do I use
STD any? I think it's pretty
straightforward as we'll see in a
minute. It's why does this exist? When
do we want to use it? And why would we
use STD any instead of something like
STD variant? All brilliant things that
we're going to be talking about today.
But first, let's talk about our sponsor
for today's video, Skillshare. I'm sure
you guys have probably heard of
Skillshare before. It's an online
learning community with thousands of
classes covering dozens of creative and
entrepreneurial skills with unlimited
access to all of these classes so that
you can join the ones that are right for
you. Since I'm more of an engineer than
an artist, I really like all of the
creative classes that Skillshare has to
offer. For example, this class is a
fantastic reference for whenever I need
to make a new logo. Skillshare are also
one of my go-to references for any time
I need to deal with web stuff. Because
let's be honest, I want to spend as
little time as possible on that. And
with these small concise videos, I can
get through this stuff quickly.
Skillshare are offering two months of
free membership to anyone who signs up
using the link in the description below.
2 months
free membership for 2 months. Think
about how much you could learn in 2
months. So, go ahead and check that out.
And I want to give a huge thank you to
Skillshare for sponsoring this video. As
you guys know, I'm quite new to doing
this YouTube thing full-time, and it's
amazing companies like that who make
this possible. Anyway, see what I did
there? I said any way because we're
talking about std::any.
Let's just jump into the code. So, the
first thing that we're going to do is
include the header file, which is just
any, just like that. Also, make sure
that you are, of course, compiling this
code with C++ 17 because this is a C++
17-only feature. It's new in C++ 17, I
should say, because obviously, if you're
using a version newer than that,
presumably, it would still be there.
Unless the committee decided that it was
a terrible idea, which
still convinced it might be. And in that
case, it's gone. But let's just pretend
that it's going to be here forever
because it might. So, to use this, you
simply write std::any. It's much like
variant, except there are no template
arguments because, of course, it's it
can store any type. Then we just will
type in a name for our variable, call it
data. You can use something called
std::make_any if you want to construct
something from here. But what we'll do
is we'll just kind of keep it empty here
and then just set data equal to like
two, for example. And then we can set
data equal to a const char, for example.
So, this will be a const char pointer.
Or we can set data equal to a string, in
which case we'll just write something
like this. Or we could set it equal to
You guys kind of get the point. You can
set it equal to like absolutely anything
because that's what it is, any
thing. If you want to retrieve your
data, you're going to have to do a
little bit more work. You'll have to
actually know which type it is and then
kind of cast it into that type. And you
can do that by using std::any_cast.
Then you just put in the type that you
want to cast to, like std::string, and
then, of course, the actual any variable
goes into the parameter here. Now, this
will throw an exception, a bad any cast
exception, if the data is not of the
type that you're trying to cast into, so
just keep that in mind. This, of course,
will return a string, so we can assign
it like so. Now, at first glance, this
may seem like it's pretty much the same
as std::variant, and that's because
well, it's similar, right? We can store
any type here, whereas std::variant
requires us to list all of our types.
But, see, whilst a lot of people might
think that std::variant is worse because
you have to list all your types, whereas
here you don't have to worry about types
at all,
that's kind of why std::variant is
actually better than std::any for pretty
much anything you need to deal with. I'm
really getting annoyed with saying the
word any all the time. The fact that
std::variant requires you to list out
all of those types is good. That's what
makes it type-safe. For example, we
might forget to explicitly write the
fact that this is a string, and we might
try and write some code like this. This
looks perfectly reasonable. We set data
to two, we set data to Cherno, which is
a string, and then we try and get that
string out. However, that's not going to
work because, well, this Cherno is not a
string, is it? It's just a const char
pointer. Whereas, if we were using
variant in this exact scenario, then our
code would look something like this. We
might have int, we might have
std::string. Now, of course, this would
work correctly, and we'd have to change
this to be get, maybe get if, because
this will get implicitly cast into a
string cuz it has to be either a string
or an int. So, are there any differences
between variant and any apart from the
fact that variant, of course, requires
you to list out the types? Well, yes,
it's to do with how they're stored.
Variant is simply a type-safe union.
What that means is that it stores all of
its data in, basically, a union. And
again, if you guys are not familiar with
that, there is a video in the top right
corner just about unions. What does any
do? Well, let's take a look. If we just
go into this header file, then we can
see all of the code for any. A lot of
people ask me, "How does this work? How
does that work?" And my answer is just
take a look. STL is a standard template
library that's implemented all in header
files, and you've got all of those
files, all that source code on your
computer. So, just open them up and try
and read it. I know it can be hard
sometimes because of the way that it's
written, but just take it slowly and
you'll be surprised at how much you'll
actually understand. So, looking at this
header file, we can start to piece
together how this actually works. We
know that storage seems to be the
variable that stores, well, something.
And you can see that what it is is
actually a union. Let's take a look at
what storage T is. It's a struct which
seems to have a small storage, a big
storage, an aligned union. And if we
actually take a look at what big storage
T, for example, is, it's a void pointer
surrounded by a bunch of padding. And
small storage is actually just an
aligned union T, which, digging in even
deeper, we realize is an aligned union
of all of the types. So, what std::any
actually does, and I think this is quite
clever, is for small types, it just
stores them as a union, which means that
for small types, it works in exactly the
same way as a variant. However, if you
have a large type, that's where it
actually takes you into that void
pointer big storage, and in that case,
it will actually dynamically allocate
memory. Now, dynamically allocating
memory is not good for performance. So,
to sum up how this works, if you're
using a variant or std::any with small
types like integers, floats, you know,
maybe like a a vector four class or
something like that like in a math
library, you'll be fine. I mean, they're
going to work in exactly the same way.
And you can see by looking here at the
source code that that small storage,
which is all the way up here, happens to
be, if we take a look at this aligned
union and specifically this any small
space size variable, you You see that it
is around 32 bytes. Now, this may be
implementation specific. Obviously, I'm
using Visual Studio with MSVC.
It's 32 bytes. So, if you have more
storage than that, at that point,
std::any will dynamically allocate.
However, std::variant will not. So, in
other words, apart from being more type
safe and a little bit more restrictive,
which is a good thing, std::variant is
also going to perform faster if you
happen to deal with larger data where
you want to avoid dynamic memory
allocation. Another tip that I can give
you for faster performance is to make
sure that you don't copy data. So, you
can see that over here with string, I am
of course copying it. If we go back to
our std::any way of doing things, you
need to make sure that you return this
by reference. And if you do that, you'll
see it doesn't work natively like this.
So, this is something that actually
would have worked with std::get. With
any cast, it doesn't. Make sure that you
actually stick the reference into the
template argument here if you're
planning to return by reference, and
that will of course make sure that
everything is nicely optimized. And you
can see that in this actual case,
obviously make sure that we actually use
std::string and not a const char
pointer. In this case, we won't actually
get any memory allocations, apart from
the one that will probably come up from
string. And it's actually very easy to
test this. You can just replace operator
new with one of your own by writing some
simple code like this. This is not a
complete good implementation of the new
operator, so don't use this in any
production code, obviously. But, if we
stick a breakpoint in here, then we'll
now be aware of all memory allocations.
And if I hit F5 to run this program,
you'll see that we do get a memory
allocation, but if we take a look at
where it comes from, it actually comes
from std::string. So, you can see over
here if I make the call stack a little
bit bigger, we have std::basic_string,
which then goes into the allocator. And
if I go back to main and I just step
through that code a little bit, so we'll
go back up here, we'll just step out of
that, and then just go to the next line.
If we take a look at this call stack a
little bit more closely, it might
actually seem like any is the one doing
the allocation cuz you can see it comes
from the assignment operator to any, but
all any is actually doing is doing a
construct in place, forwarding all those
arguments, and it's the basic string,
you can see, that is allocating once
again. So, F5 to continue running this,
and again, we have a basic string, and
that is all of the allocations from this
program. So, in that case, std::any
actually did not allocate anything. If,
however, we were to have some kind of
class that would have more than 32
bytes. So, for example, I'll have a
struct here of two strings, S0 and S1.
If I do try and actually set this up
over here, I'll just use custom class,
and we will remove this any cast. If I
hit F5, if I skip past this basic string
allocation, that of course is coming
from the member variables of that custom
class, then you'll see that what we have
here is that assignment operator, and
during the in-placement, you can see
that this is a big storage operation,
which of course does actually call new
over here. So, just be aware that
std::any will allocate if it needs to,
and in this case, if the data that
you're trying to store is above 32
bytes, you can see that it calls new and
causes a dynamic memory allocation. So,
back to the question of when to use
std::any. When should it be used?
This is a tricky one. A lot of people
will just flat out tell you that it's
just a bit useless, and to be honest,
I'm kind of inclined to agree. When
What like What is a good use case for
std::any? If you want to store multiple
data types in a single variable, use
std::variant. It's basically a type-safe
version of std::any, meaning that you
can't set it to whatever type you please
accidentally, and also, it's not going
to dynamically allocate memory, so it
will perform better. If you have the
need, the requirement to be able to
store any data type in a single
variable,
maybe rethink the design of your
program. I mean, I honestly
really like can't think of a valid use
case for this. I think that it's
I think that it's something that you
probably should never use. I mean, if
you have like a buffer of data and you
have like absolutely no idea what that
data is, you just want to you just want
to point it to it, then that's fine. You
can use a void pointer for that. But
this is like this is something
completely different. If you guys have
any good use cases, if you guys have
used this throughout your code and you
think that it's useful, please drop a
comment below. I'd love to read some of
those comments and see because as it
stands right now, I don't think this is
anywhere near as useful as optional or
variant and it's kind of
funny, I guess, to end to end the series
on something like this, but that's just
the way it is. I just think that
std::any is
is something that you should definitely
be aware of, but maybe not something
that you should use all that often.
Anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this
video. If you did, you can hit that like
button. Also, don't forget to check out
the link in the description for 2 months
of free Skillshare membership. You can
also drop a comment below if you want me
to cover a specific topic in C++
and I will add it to my ever-growing
list. I will see you guys next time.
Goodbye.